Guide to the Alexander Weinmann Papers, 1614-1986 RL.01359
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Alexander Weinmann papers
1614-1986
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Weinmann, Alexander, 1901-1987
RL.01359
14 Linear Feet
7,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Portions of the Alexander Weinmann Papers are restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Alexander Weinmann Papers (1614-1986) were purchased by the Duke University David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1988.
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1901, Feb. 20 Born, Vienna, Austria
1948 Published Werkverzeichnis Joseph Lanner
1952 Published Artaria and Co.
1955 Completed Vollständiges Verlagsverzeichnis Artaria und Comp. (Dissertation) Received a doctorate in musicology, Innsbruck University
1956 Published Werkverzeichnis Johann Strauss Vater und Sohn Published Weiner Musikverleger und Musikalienhändler von Mozarts Zeit bis gegen 1860
1964 Published Franz Anton Hoffmeister
1973 Published 'Das Grab' ein literarisch-musikalischer Bestseller in Österreichische Musikzeitschrift
1987 Died, Vienna, Austria
Weinmann's works in Viennese music publishing are included in the Beiträge zur Geschichte des Alt-Weiner Musikverlages series. He also published a number of articles in the field of musicology in the Österreichische Musikzeitschrift. He was a contributor to the Répertoire international des sources musicales and the New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians, and a co-editor of L. von Köchel: Chronologisch-thematisches Verzeichnis sämtlicher Tonwerke Wolfgang Amadé Mozarts (Sixth Edition).
Collection Overview
The collection reflects Weinmann's extensive research in the history of Viennese music publishing and is a resource for study of publishing firms in Vienna as well as documenting Weinmann's bibliographical research. The Music Series includes title pages and parts of arrangements, focusing on Viennese publishers and composers, including Georg Druschetzky, Joseph Haydn, Johann Baptist Vanhal, Johann Josef Rösler, and Ferdinand Kauer, as well as Johann Sebastian Bach. Included in the Writings and Speeches Series are manuscript drafts of works related to Weinmann's bibliographies (published in the Beiträge zur Geschichte des Alt-Weiner Musikverlages) as well as bio-bibliographical and historical works. The series also documents Weinmann's study of 19th century Viennese publishing firms including Artaria and Company, Giovanni Cappi, Leopold Kozeluch, Franz Anton Hoffmeister, Carlo and Pietro Mechetti, Tranquillo Mollo, Ignaz Sauer, Johann Traeg, and Thaddäus Weigl. Series includes research by Weinmann's brother, Ignaz Weinmann, on Franz Schubert.
The Research Notes Series consists of bibliographic references and citations, information about works and plate numbers; Weinmann's contributions to the Répertoire international des sources musicales; and Wiener Zeitung references. The Series also concerns Weinmann's work as an editor of the sixth edition of the Chronologisch-thematisches Verzeichnis sämtlicher Tonwerke Wolfgang Amadé Mozarts. Anthony van Hoboken, Willi Boskovsky, Franz Giegling, Anton Fietz, and Arthur Fiedler are among primary correspondents in the collection. Weinmann also collected letters (originals and copies) from persons and publishers he studied, including J.P. Gotthard, Johann Strauss, Franz Xaver Süssmayr, and Tobias Haslinger.
Music -- Publishing -- Austria -- Vienna; Music -- Bio-bibliography; Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828; Sauer, Ignaz; Sussmayr, Franz Xaver; Strauss, Johann; Mechetti, Pietro; Mechetti, Carlo; Rvsler, Johann Josef, 1771-1813; Mollo, Tranquillo; Weinmann, Ignaz; Vanhal, Jan Baptist, 1739-1813; Traeg, Johann, fl. 1782-1805; Weigl, Thaddaus; Boskovsky, Willi, 1909-1991; Druschetzky, Georg, 1745-1819; Fietz, Anton; Giegling, Franz, 1921-; Anton Diabelli; Artaria and Company; Bach, Johann Sabastian, 1685-1750; Hoboken, Anthony van, 1881-; Hoffmeister, Franz Anton; Kauer, Ferdinand, 1751-1831; Kozeluch, Leopold; Giovanni Cappi; Gotthard, J.P., 1839-1919; Haslinger, Tobias; Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1808
- Correspondence, 1614-1986, undated (bulk 1932-1986)
  Scope and Contents note
  Primarily correspondence between Weinmann and other scholars, musicians, conductors, and librarians. However, the early correspondence (1614-1928) is originals and copies of letters by Franz Xaver Süssmayr, Tobias Haslinger and J.P. Gotthard which Weinmann collected.
  - 1614-1986, Feb. 14, undated, 28 folders (Box 1)
- Writings and Speeches, 1931-1985, undated
  Includes typescripts and handwritten drafts of writings by Weinmann, some works published in the Beiträge zur Geschichte des Alt-Wiener Musikverlages as well as extensive lists and notes. At the end is a chronological arrangement of works which were not directly or solely identified as pertaining to the composers or publishers. Arranged alphabetically by composers, publishers, and works.
  - Artaria and Co., 1953 (Box 2)
  - Beethoven, 1980, undated (Box 2)
  - Cappi, 1958, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Diabelli, Anton, 1954-1985, undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Druschetzky, Georg, 1967, undated (Box 2)
  - Eder, Joseph - Bermann, J., undated (Box 2)
  - Fietz, Anton, 1950s-1979, undated (Box 2)
  - D-F (Box 2)
  - Das Grab, 1960s, undated (Box 2)
  - Haslinger, Tobias, 1943-1980, undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Haydn, Joseph, 1973-1982, undated (Box 2)
  - Hoffmeister, Franz Anton, 1960s-1985, undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Kauer, Ferdinand, undated (Box 2)
  - Kostbarkeiten aus Alt-Wien, 1960s, undated (Box 2)
  - Lindemayr, Maurus, 1972- 1976, undated (Box 2)
  - G-L (Box 2)
  - Mechetti, Carlo and Pietro, 1958, undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Mollo, Tranquillo, undated (Box 2)
  - von Mosel, Ignaz Franz, undated (Box 2)
  - Mozart, Leopold, undated (Box 2)
  - Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1965-1985, n.d, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Muller, Adolf, Hans-Christian, Heinrich Friedrich, 1977, undated (Box 2)
  - Pleyel, Ignaz, 1958-1977 (Box 2)
  - Radio lectures, recording, 1961-1980, undated (Box 2)
  - RISM, 1967- 1977, undated (Box 2)
  - Sauer, Ignaz (and Leidesdor), undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Schubert, Franz, 1972-1985, undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Die Schubert-Sammlung im Musikarchiv der Benediltinerabtei Seitenstetten, 1976 (Ignaz Weinmann) (Box 3)
  - Die Schubert-Sammlung im Musikarchiv des Stiftes Seitenstetten, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Steffan, Josef Anton, undated (Box 3)
  - Strauss, Johann, 1948-1976, undated (Box 3)
  - S (Box 3)
  - Traeg, Johann, 1977-1978, undated(3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Weigl, Thaddäus, 1982, undated (Box 3)
  - Wiener Musikverlag Am Rande, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)
  - 1931-1983, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - 1984- 1985, undated, 12 folders (Box 4)
- Research Notes, 1823-1985, undated
  Includes bibliographic references, notes for publishers' and composers' biographies, annotated printed material, information from Wiener Zeitung about publishers, and other fragments of information pertaining to the publishers and composers whom Weinmann studied. These materials are arranged chronologically, but most of the material is undated. Following the chronological arrangement are materials and correspondence with Franz Giegling concerning the sixth edition of the Ludwig Ritter von Köchel: Chronologisch-thematisches Verzeichnis sämtlicher Tonwerke Wolfgang Amadé Mozarts (Köchel-Verzeichnis). Both Weinmann and Giegling were editors of the Sixth Edition.
  - 1823-1985, undated, 8 folders (Box 4)
  - undated, 12 folders (Box 5)
  - Köchel-Verzeichnis:
    - 1957- 1984, 6 folders (Box 5)
    - Photographs, 1964, undated, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Mozart, W. A., undated (Box 6)
    - 1962-1985 (Box 6)
  - Negatives, B-W, undated (Box 6)
- Music Series, 1601-1976, undated
  Includes arrangements, fragments, and title pages of published music (originals and photocopies). Also contains manuscript examples prepared by Weinmann. Arranged by format: paper, photographs, and negatives. Within each format the materials are arranged alphabetically by composer, publisher, or title. When holdings include more than one work by a composer or publisher, works are arranged alphabetically by the title of the work.
  - Music Series: Paper
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Portions of this series are restricted.
    - Albrechtsberger, Anton, ca. 1976? (Box 6)
    - Albrechtsberger, Johann Georg, 1976 (?), 1781- (?), 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Albrechtsberger, Johann Georg, 1786-(?) (Box 6)
    - Artaria and Co., undated (Box 6)
    - Auber, Daniel, undated (Box 6)
    - Beethoven, Ludwig Von, 1828, undated (Box 6)
    - Cappi und Diabelli, undated (Box 6)
    - Das Grab, 1815-(?) (Box 6)
    - Dessauer, Josef, undated (Box 6)
    - Diabelli, undated (Box 6)
    - Druschetzky, Georg, undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Eybler, Joseph, undated (Box 6)
    - Fietz, Anton, 1952 (Box 6)
    - Hackel, Anton, undated (Box 6)
    - Haydn, Joseph, undated (Box 6)
    - Herold, F., undated (Box 6)
    - Hoffmeister, Franz, 1839, undated (Box 6)
    - Kozeluch, Leopold, undated (Box 6)
    - Kreutzer, Rodolphe, 1601, undated (Box 6)
    - Liszt, Franz, undated (Box 6)
    - Lortzing, Gustave, undated (Box 6)
    - Mechetti, Carlo and Pietro, undated (Box 6)
    - Mollo, Tranquillo, undated (Box 6)
    - Mosel, J. F., 1822, undated (Box 6)
    - Mozart, W. A., 1847, undated, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Müller, Adolf, undated (Box 6)
    - Pleyl, Ignaz, 1790, undated (Box 6)
    - Proch, Heinrich, undated (Box 6)
    - Resnitschek, I., undated (Box 6)
    - Schubert, Franz, undated, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Steffan, Joseph, undated (Box 6)
    - Strauss, Eduard und Anton, 1821 (Box 6)
    - Vanhal, Johann Baptist, undated, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Vogel, Wilhelm, undated (Box 6)
    - Zechner, 1976 (Box 6)
    - Hymns, undated (Box 6)
    - Dance Music, undated (Box 6)
    - Songs, ca. 1854, undated (Box 6)
    - Various Composers, A-N, undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Various composers, O-Z, undated (Box 7)
    - Title pages, undated (Box 7)
    - Anonymous, 1987 [?] (Box 7)
    - Unidentified and miscellaneous fragments, 1933-1952 [?] (Box 7)
  - Music Series: Photographs
    - Anonymous with titles, undated:
      - Allegro für Klavier und Violine, Concerto für Violoncello princ., 2 v, 2 ve, 2 0b, 2 Cor, Basso, undated (Box 7)
      - Divertimentos, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Für die Viola d'Amor Cruittaré and Kleine Stücke (Box 7)
      - Recitativo - Violino, Basso and Organo Sonata, Te Deum Royel (Box 7)
      - Violino Solo and Violino Grand Trio (Box 7)
      - Anonymous, 1820, undated, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Beethoven, Ludwig Van, undated (Box 7)
    - Druschetsky, Georg, Concerto in B and F. undated (Box 7)
    - Druschetzky, Georg:
      - Six Parthies, undated (Box 7)
      - Grand Septetto, 1886 (Box 7)
    - Eybler, Giuseppe, n.d (Box 7)
    - Haydn, Josef:
      - Variatrone per ie Clavi Cembalo, undated (Box 7)
      - A-Z, undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Hoffmeister, Francesco, undated (Box 7)
    - Josephz, E. Lebas, 1760 (Box 7)
    - Klein, Henri, Six Contre Danses, undated (Box 7)
    - Licki, C. Georg, Trio für Clarinette, Fagotte, Horn, 1806 (Box 7)
    - Mozart, W. A, undated, 6 folders (Box 8)
    - Rösler, Johann Josef, Partita für 3 Bassethörner, undated (Box 8)
    - Schubert, Franz:
      - Compositionen, n.d (Box 8)
      - Schubertiana, 1814-1973 (Box 8)
    - Steffan, Joseph, undated
      - Allegro Vivace (Box 8)
      - Un die Verklärte Theresia, 1781 (Box 8)
      - Variazioni Combinate in C (Box 8)
      - Variazioni Combinate per il Forte e Piano (Box 8)
    - Druschetzky, Concerte, undated (Box 8)
    - Tuma, Franz, Stabar Mater, undated (Box 8)
    - Vanhal, Johann:
      - Unidentified, undated (Box 8)
      - A-Z, undated, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Wallfarths Gesanger, 1689 (Box 8)
    - Werner, Gregor Joseph, 1759 (Box 8)
    - Ziegler, Josef, undated (Box 8)
    - Various composers, undated, 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1725, 1867, undated (Box 9)
    - Various title pages, 1766- 1874, undated, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Unidentified, 1821-1869, undated, 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Music Series: Negatives
    - Negatives, undated (Box 10)
    - Negatives and miscellaneous, undated (Box 11)
- Printed Material, 1871-1986, undated (bulk 1949-1985)
  Contains programs, brochures, photocopies, and annotations on items pertaining to concerts and performances.
  - 1871-1975, undated, 10 folders (Box 11)
  - 1976-1986, undated, 16 folders (Box 12)
- Books and Catalogs, undated
  Includes photographs, photocopies, and negatives. Books are arranged alphabetically by author and then chronologically. Catalogs and Negatives are filed alphabetically by title.
  - Books, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Catalogs, 4 folders (Box 12)
  - Negatives, 2 folders (Box 12)
- Miscellaneous, 1701-1991, undated
  Includes clippings, phonograph records, photographs, and negatives.
  - 1701-1983,undated, 4 folders (Box 12)
  - undated (Box 13)
  - Clippings, 1933- 1985, undated (Box 13)
  - Phonograph records. 1960- 1962, undated (Box 13)
  - Photographs, 1730-1991, undated, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Negatives, 1961, undated, 5 folders (Box 14)
- Oversize Material
  - Writings and Speeches Series
    - Artaria and Company, undated, 4 folders (Box 15)
    - Diabelli, Anton, undated (Box 15)
    - Glöggl, F. X., undated (Box 15)
    - Gotthard, J. P., undated (Box 15)
    - Haslinger, Tobais, undated (Box 15)
    - Lithogr Institut nächst der Burg No. 2, undated (Box 15)
    - Mechetti, Carlo and Pietro, undated (Box 15)
    - Mollo, Tranquillo, undated (Box 15)
    - Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, undated (Box 15)
    - Müller, H. F., undated (Box 16)
    - Rörich, Franz, undated (Box 16)
    - Senefelder, undated (Box 16)
    - S. A. Steiner and Co., undated (Box 16)
    - Weigl, Thaddäus, undated (Box 16)
    - 1954-1982, undated (Box 16)
    - undated,1026-15451, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous Series
    - Clippings, circa 1929-1985, undated, 6 folders (Box 17)
    - Clippings, circa 1850s-1970s (Oversize-folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Mostly clippings from German newspapers.
  - Research Notes
    - undated (Box 18)
  - Music Series
    - Composers: (Box 18)
      - Mozart, Leopold, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - A-Z, undated (Box 18)
      - Schubert, Franz (Box 18)
      - D-V (Box 18)
    - Various composers, undated (Box 18)
  - Printed Material
    - 1826-1985, undated, 8 folders (Box 18)
- Audio tapes
  Conditions Governing Access
  Audio tapes require digitization prior to use. For more information, contact Rubenstein Library Staff.
  Series contains homemade recordings from commercially released phonodiscs or tapes, with portions of the content including audio commentary from Weinmann.
  - Dances from Old Vienna; The Good Old Times (Willi Boskovsky), homemade audio cassette tapes from phonodisc or audio tape
    - Audio cassette I (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL01359-CS-0001)
    - Audio cassette II, with commentary by Weinmann (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL01359-CS-0002)
    - Audio cassette III, with commentary by Weinmann (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL01359-CS-0003)
    - Audio cassette IV (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL01359-CS-0004)
  - Collegium Musicum Pragense, Supraphon 0110614 [Musica Antiqua Bohemica: Hunting Music (1970)], homemade audio tape from phonodisc or tape
    - 1/4-inch audio reel (Box 19, Audio-reel RL01359-RR-0001)
- Addition (2002-0141), 1940s-1991 (Box Acc. 02/141: 1-3)
  The addition to the collection (2002-0141) (752 items, 1.4 linear feet; dated [ca. 1940s]-1991 and undated) contains research notes, 101 photo stats and other types of musical score copies, and other materials used by Weinmann for producing his Johan Baptist Vanhal catalog. Includes correspondence to Paul Bryan from and, after his death, about Weinmann (1969-1991); Bryan's notes and correspondence regarding the Weinmann collection at Duke; publications by Weinmann; two audio cassettes of conversations between Bryan and Weinmann and others; and 1 color slide, ca. 30 color prints, and 2 black-and-white prints of Weinmann and his family (circa 1940s, 1975, and undated). This accession is unprocessed; there is no container list for this material.